=== WAIT EVENTS FULL ===
40000 chars
10
Instance Tuning Using Performance Views
After the initial configuration of a database, monitoring and tuning an instance regularly is
important to eliminate any potential performance bottlenecks. This chapter discusses the
tuning process using Oracle V$ performance views.
This chapter contains the following sections:
ò
Instance Tuning Steps
ò
Interpreting Oracle Database Statistics
ò
Wait Events Statistics
ò
Tuning Instance Recovery Performance: Fast-Start Fault Recovery
Instance Tuning Steps
These are the main steps in the Oracle performance method for instance tuning:
1.
Define the Problem
Get candid feedback from users about the scope of the performance problem.
2.
Examine the Host System and Examine the Oracle Database Statistics
ò
After obtaining a full set of operating system, database, and application statistics,
examine the data for any evidence of performance problems.
ò
Consider the list of common performance errors to see whether the data gathered
suggests that they are contributing to the problem.
ò
Build a conceptual model of what is happening on the system using the performance
data gathered.
3.
Implement and Measure Change
Propose changes to be made and the expected result of implementing the changes.
Then, implement the changes and measure application performance.
4.
Determine whether the performance objective defined in step 1 has been met. If not, then
repeat steps 2 and 3 until the performance goals are met.
The remainder of this chapter discusses instance tuning using the Oracle Database dynamic
performance views. However, Oracle recommends using Automatic Workload Repository
(AWR) and Automatic Database Diagnostic Monitor (ADDM) for statistics gathering,
monitoring, and tuning due to the extended feature list.
Note:
If your site does not have AWR and ADDM features, then you can use Statspack to
gather Oracle database instance statistics.
10-1
Define the Problem
It is vital to develop a good understanding of the purpose of the tuning exercise and
the nature of the problem before attempting to implement a solution. Without this
understanding, it is virtually impossible to implement effective changes. The data
gathered during this stage helps determine the next step to take and what evidence to
examine.
Gather the following data:
1.
Identify the performance objective.
What is the measure of acceptable performance? How many transactions an hour,
or seconds, response time will meet the required performance level?
2.
Identify the scope of the problem.
What is affected by the slowdown? For example, is the whole instance slow? Is it a
particular application, program, specific operation, or a single user?
3.
Identify the time frame when the problem occurs.
Is the problem only evident during peak hours? Does performance deteriorate over
the course of the day? Was the slowdown gradual (over the space of months or
weeks) or sudden?
4.
Quantify the slowdown.
This helps identify the extent of the problem and also acts as a measure for
comparison when deciding whether changes implemented to fix the problem have
actually made an improvement. Find a consistently reproducible measure of the
response time or job run time. How much worse are the timings than when the
program was running well?
5.
Identify any changes.
Identify what has changed since performance was acceptable. This may narrow
the potential cause quickly. For example, has the operating system software,
hardware, application software, or Oracle Database release been upgraded? Has
more data been loaded into the system, or has the data volume or user population
grown?
At the end of this phase, you should have a good understanding of the symptoms. If
the symptoms can be identified as local to a program or set of programs, then the
problem is handled in a different manner from instance-wide performance issues.
Examine the Host System
Look at the load on the database server and the database instance. Consider the
operating system, the I/O subsystem, and network statistics, because examining these
areas helps determine what might be worth further investigation. In multitier systems,
also examine the application server middle-tier hosts.
Examining the host hardware often gives a strong indication of the bottleneck in the
system. This determines which Oracle Database performance data could be useful for
cross-reference and further diagnosis.
Data to examine includes the following:
ò
CPU Usage
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-2
ò
Identifying I/O Problems
ò
Identifying Network Issues
CPU Usage
If there is a significant amount of idle CPU, then there could be an I/O, application, or
database bottleneck. Note that wait I/O should be considered as idle CPU.
If there is high CPU usage, then determine whether the CPU is being used effectively. Is the
majority of CPU usage attributable to a small number of high-CPU using programs, or is the
CPU consumed by an evenly distributed workload?
If a small number of high-usage programs use the CPU, then look at the programs to
determine the cause. Check whether some processes alone consume the full power of one
CPU. Depending on the process, this could indicate a CPU or process-bound workload that
can be tackled by dividing or parallelizing process activity.
Non-Oracle Processes
If the programs are not Oracle programs, then identify whether they are legitimately requiring
that amount of CPU. If so, determine whether their execution be delayed to off-peak hours.
Identifying these CPU intensive processes can also help narrowing what specific activity,
such as I/O, network, and paging, is consuming resources and how can it be related to the
database workload.
Oracle Processes
If a small number of Oracle processes consumes most of the CPU resources, then use
SQL_TRACE and TKPROF to identify the SQL or PL/SQL statements to see if a particular query
or PL/SQL program unit can be tuned. For example, a SELECT statement could be CPU-
intensive if its execution involves many reads of data in cache (logical reads) that could be
avoided with better SQL optimization.
Oracle Database CPU Statistics
Oracle Database CPU statistics are available in several V$ views:
ò
V$SYSSTAT shows Oracle Database CPU usage for all sessions. The CPU used by this
session statistic shows the aggregate CPU used by all sessions. The parse time cpu
statistic shows the total CPU time used for parsing.
ò
V$SESSTAT shows Oracle Database CPU usage for each session. Use this view to
determine which particular session is using the most CPU.
ò
V$RSRC_CONSUMER_GROUP shows CPU utilization statistics for each consumer group when
the Oracle Database Resource Manager is running.
Interpreting CPU Statistics
It is important to recognize that CPU time and real time are distinct. With eight CPUs, for any
given minute in real time, there are eight minutes of CPU time available. On Windows and
UNIX, this can be either user time or system time (privileged mode on Windows). Thus,
average CPU time utilized by all processes (threads) on the system could be greater than
one minute for every one minute real time interval.
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-3
At any given moment, you know how much time Oracle Database has used on the
system. So, if eight minutes are available and Oracle Database uses four minutes of
that time, then you know that 50% of all CPU time is used by Oracle. If your process is
not consuming that time, then some other process is. Identify the processes that are
using CPU time, figure out why, and then attempt to tune them.
If the CPU usage is evenly distributed over many Oracle server processes, examine
the V$SYS_TIME_MODEL view to help get a precise understanding of where most time is
spent.
See Also:
"Table 10-1" for more information about various wait events and their
possible causes
Identifying I/O Problems
An overly active I/O system can be evidenced by disk queue lengths greater than two,
or disk service times that are over 20-30ms. If the I/O system is overly active, then
check for potential hot spots that could benefit from distributing the I/O across more
disks. Also identify whether the load can be reduced by lowering the resource
requirements of the programs using those resources. If the I/O problems are caused
by Oracle Database, then I/O tuning can begin. If Oracle Database is not consuming
the available I/O resources, then identify the process that is using up the I/O.
Determine why the process is using up the I/O, and then tune this process.
I/O problems can be identified using V$ views in Oracle Database and monitoring tools
in the operating system, as described in the following sections:
ò
Identifying I/O Problems Using V$ Views
ò
Identifying I/O Problems Using Operating System Monitoring Tools
Identifying I/O Problems Using V$ Views
Check the Oracle wait event data in V$SYSTEM_EVENT to see whether the top wait
events are I/O related. I/O related events include db file sequential read, db file
scattered read, db file single write, db file parallel write, and log file
parallel write. These are all events corresponding to I/Os performed against data
files and log files. If any of these wait events correspond to high average time, then
investigate the I/O contention.
Cross reference the host I/O system data with the I/O sections in the Automatic
Repository report to identify hot data files and tablespaces. Also compare the I/O times
reported by the operating system with the times reported by Oracle Database to see if
they are consistent.
An I/O problem can also manifest itself with non-I/O related wait events. For example,
the difficulty in finding a free buffer in the buffer cache or high wait times for logs to be
flushed to disk can also be symptoms of an I/O problem. Before investigating whether
the I/O system should be reconfigured, determine if the load on the I/O system can be
reduced.
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-4
To reduce I/O load caused by Oracle Database, examine the I/O statistics collected for all I/O
calls made by the database using the following views:
ò
V$IOSTAT_CONSUMER_GROUP
The V$IOSTAT_CONSUMER_GROUP view captures I/O statistics for consumer groups. If
Oracle Database Resource Manager is enabled, I/O statistics for all consumer groups
that are part of the currently enabled resource plan are captured.
ò
V$IOSTAT_FILE
The V$IOSTAT_FILE view captures I/O statistics of database files that are or have been
accessed. The SMALL_SYNC_READ_LATENCY column displays the latency for single block
synchronous reads (in milliseconds), which translates directly to the amount of time that
clients need to wait before moving onto the next operation. This defines the
responsiveness of the storage subsystem based on the current load. If there is a high
latency for critical data files, you may want to consider relocating these files to improve
their service time. To calculate latency statistics, timed_statistics must be set to TRUE.
ò
V$IOSTAT_FUNCTION
The V$IOSTAT_FUNCTION view captures I/O statistics for database functions (such as the
LGWR and DBWR).
An I/O can be issued by various Oracle processes with different functionalities. The top
database functions are classified in the V$IOSTAT_FUNCTION view. In cases when there is
a conflict of I/O functions, the I/O is placed in the bucket with the lower FUNCTION_ID. For
example, if XDB issues an I/O from the buffer cache, the I/O would be classified as an
XDB I/O because it has a lower FUNCTION_ID value. Any unclassified function is placed in
the Others bucket. You can display the FUNCTION_ID hierarchy by querying the
V$IOSTAT_FUNCTION view:
select FUNCTION_ID, FUNCTION_NAME
from v$iostat_function
order by FUNCTION_ID;
FUNCTION_ID FUNCTION_NAME
----------- ------------------
 0 RMAN
 1 DBWR
 2 LGWR
 3 ARCH
 4 XDB
 5 Streams AQ
 6 Data Pump
 7 Recovery
 8 Buffer Cache Reads
 9 Direct Reads
 10 Direct Writes
 11 Others
These V$IOSTAT views contains I/O statistics for both single and multi block read and write
operations. Single block operations are small I/Os that are less than or equal to 128 kilobytes.
Multi block operations are large I/Os that are greater than 128 kilobytes. For each of these
operations, the following statistics are collected:
ò
Identifier
ò
Total wait time (in milliseconds)
ò
Number of waits executed (for consumer groups and functions)
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-5
ò
Number of requests for each operation
ò
Number of single and multi block bytes read
ò
Number of single and multi block bytes written
You should also look at SQL statements that perform many physical reads by querying
the V$SQLAREA view, or by reviewing the "SQL ordered by Reads" section of the
Automatic Workload Repository report. Examine these statements to see how they can
be tuned to reduce the number of I/Os.
See Also:
Oracle Database Reference for more information about the views
V$IOSTAT_CONSUMER_GROUP, V$IOSTAT_FUNCTION, V$IOSTAT_FILE, and
V$SQLAREA
Identifying I/O Problems Using Operating System Monitoring Tools
Use operating system monitoring tools to determine what processes are running on
the system as a whole and to monitor disk access to all files. Remember that disks
holding data files and redo log files can also hold files that are not related to Oracle
Database. Reduce any heavy access to disks that contain database files. You can
monitor access to non-database files only through operating system facilities, rather
than through the V$ views.
Utilities, such as sar -d (or iostat) on many UNIX systems and the administrative
performance monitoring tool on Windows systems, examine I/O statistics for the entire
system.
See Also:
Your operating system documentation for the tools available on your platform
Identifying Network Issues
Using operating system utilities, look at the network round-trip ping time and the
number of collisions. If the network is causing large delays in response time, then
investigate possible causes.
To identify network I/O caused by remote access of database files, examine the
V$IOSTAT_NETWORK view. This view contains network I/O statistics caused by accessing
files on a remote database instance, including:
ò
Database client initiating the network I/O (such as RMAN and PLSQL)
ò
Number of read and write operations issued
ò
Number of kilobytes read and written
ò
Total wait time in milliseconds for read operations
ò
Total wait in milliseconds for write operations
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-6
After the cause of the network issue is identified, network load can be reduced by scheduling
large data transfers to off-peak times, or by coding applications to batch requests to remote
hosts, rather than accessing remote hosts once (or more) for one request.
Examine the Oracle Database Statistics
Examine Oracle Database statistics and cross-reference them with operating system
statistics to ensure a consistent diagnosis of the problem. Operating system statistics can
indicate a good place to begin tuning. However, if the goal is to tune the Oracle database
instance, then look at the Oracle Database statistics to identify the resource bottleneck from a
database perspective before implementing corrective action.
This section contains the following topics.
ò
Setting the Level of Statistics Collection
ò
Wait Events
ò
Dynamic Performance Views Containing Wait Event Statistics
ò
System Statistics
ò
Segment-Level Statistics
See Also:
"Interpreting Oracle Database Statistics"
Setting the Level of Statistics Collection
Oracle Database provides the initialization parameter STATISTICS_LEVEL, which controls all
major statistics collections or advisories in the database. This parameter sets the statistics
collection level for the database.
Depending on the setting of STATISTICS_LEVEL, certain advisories or statistics are collected,
as follows:
ò
BASIC: No advisories or statistics are collected. Monitoring and many automatic features
are disabled. Oracle does not recommend this setting because it disables important
Oracle Database features.
ò
TYPICAL: This is the default value and ensures collection for all major statistics while
providing best overall database performance. This setting should be adequate for most
environments.
ò
ALL: All of the advisories or statistics that are collected with the TYPICAL setting are
included, plus timed operating system statistics and row source execution statistics.
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-7
See Also:
ò
Oracle Database Reference for more information on the
STATISTICS_LEVEL initialization parameter.
ò
Oracle Database Reference for information about the
V$STATISTICS_LEVEL view. This view lists the status of the statistics or
advisories controlled by the STATISTICS_LEVEL initialization parameter.
Wait Events
Wait events are statistics that are incremented by a server process or thread to
indicate that it had to wait for an event to complete before being able to continue
processing. Wait event data reveals various symptoms of problems that might be
impacting performance, such as latch contention, buffer contention, and I/O
contention. Remember that these are only symptoms of problems, not the actual
causes.
Wait events are grouped into classes. The wait event classes include: Administrative,
Application, Cluster, Commit, Concurrency, Configuration, Idle, Network, Other,
Scheduler, System I/O, and User I/O.
A server process can wait for the following:
ò
A resource to become available, such as a buffer or a latch.
ò
An action to complete, such as an I/O.
ò
More work to do, such as waiting for the client to provide the next SQL statement
to execute. Events that identify that a server process is waiting for more work are
known as idle events.
Wait event statistics include the number of times an event was waited for and the time
waited for the event to complete. If the initialization parameter TIMED_STATISTICS is set
to true, then you can also see how long each resource was waited for.
To minimize user response time, reduce the time spent by server processes waiting for
event completion. Not all wait events have the same wait time. Therefore, it is more
important to examine events with the most total time waited rather than wait events
with a high number of occurrences. Usually, it is best to set the dynamic parameter
TIMED_STATISTICS to true at least while monitoring performance.
See Also:
ò
"Wait Events Statistics"
ò
"Using Wait Events with Timed Statistics"
ò
Oracle Database Reference for more information about Oracle Database
wait events
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-8
Dynamic Performance Views Containing Wait Event Statistics
These dynamic performance views can be queried for wait event statistics:
ò
V$ACTIVE_SESSION_HISTORY
The V$ACTIVE_SESSION_HISTORY view displays active database session activity, sampled
once every second.
ò
V$SESS_TIME_MODEL and V$SYS_TIME_MODEL
The V$SESS_TIME_MODEL and V$SYS_TIME_MODEL views contain time model statistics,
including DB time which is the total time spent in database calls.
ò
V$SESSION_WAIT
The V$SESSION_WAIT view displays information about the current or last wait for each
session (such as wait ID, class, and time).
ò
V$SESSION
The V$SESSION view displays information about each current session and contains the
same wait statistics as those found in the V$SESSION_WAIT view. If applicable, this view
also contains detailed information about the object that the session is currently waiting for
(such as object number, block number, file number, and row number), the blocking
session responsible for the current wait (such as the blocking session ID, status, and
type), and the amount of time waited.
ò
V$SESSION_EVENT
The V$SESSION_EVENT view provides summary of all the events the session has waited for
since it started.
ò
V$SESSION_WAIT_CLASS
The V$SESSION_WAIT_CLASS view provides the number of waits and the time spent in
each class of wait events for each session.
ò
V$SESSION_WAIT_HISTORY
The V$SESSION_WAIT_HISTORY view displays information about the last ten wait events for
each active session (such as event type and wait time).
ò
V$SYSTEM_EVENT
The V$SYSTEM_EVENT view provides a summary of all the event waits on the instance
since it started.
ò
V$EVENT_HISTOGRAM
The V$EVENT_HISTOGRAM view displays a histogram of the number of waits, the maximum
wait, and total wait time on an event basis.
ò
V$FILE_HISTOGRAM
The V$FILE_HISTOGRAM view displays a histogram of times waited during single block
reads for each file.
ò
V$SYSTEM_WAIT_CLASS
The V$SYSTEM_WAIT_CLASS view provides the instance wide time totals for the number of
waits and the time spent in each class of wait events.
ò
V$TEMP_HISTOGRAM
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-9
The V$TEMP_HISTOGRAM view displays a histogram of times waited during single
block reads for each temporary file.
Investigate wait events and related timing data when performing reactive performance
tuning. The events with the most time listed against them are often strong indications
of the performance bottleneck. For example, by looking at V$SYSTEM_EVENT, you might
notice lots of buffer busy waits. It might be that many processes are inserting into the
same block and must wait for each other before they can insert. The solution could be
to use automatic segment space management or partitioning for the object in question.
See Also:
ò
"Wait Events Statistics" for differences among the views
V$SESSION_WAIT, V$SESSION_EVENT, and V$SYSTEM_EVENT
ò
Oracle Database Reference for information about the dynamic
performance views
System Statistics
System statistics are typically used in conjunction with wait event data to find further
evidence of the cause of a performance problem.
For example, if V$SYSTEM_EVENT indicates that the largest wait event (in terms of wait
time) is the event buffer busy waits, then look at the specific buffer wait statistics
available in the view V$WAITSTAT to see which block type has the highest wait count
and the highest wait time.
After the block type has been identified, also look at V$SESSION real-time while the
problem is occurring or V$ACTIVE_SESSION_HISTORY and
DBA_HIST_ACTIVE_SESS_HISTORY views after the problem has been experienced to
identify the contended-for objects using the object number indicated. The combination
of this data indicates the appropriate corrective action.
Statistics are available in many V$ views. The following are some of the V$ views that
contain system statistics.
V$ACTIVE_SESSION_HISTORY
This view displays active database session activity, sampled once every second.
V$SYSSTAT
This contains overall statistics for many different parts of Oracle Database, including
rollback, logical and physical I/O, and parse data. Data from V$SYSSTAT is used to
compute ratios, such as the buffer cache hit ratio.
V$FILESTAT
This contains detailed file I/O statistics for each file, including the number of I/Os for
each file and the average read time.
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-10
V$ROLLSTAT
This contains detailed rollback and undo segment statistics for each segment.
V$ENQUEUE_STAT
This contains detailed enqueue statistics for each enqueue, including the number of times an
enqueue was requested and the number of times an enqueue was waited for, and the wait
time.
V$LATCH
This contains detailed latch usage statistics for each latch, including the number of times
each latch was requested and the number of times the latch was waited for.
See Also:
Oracle Database Reference for information about dynamic performance views
Segment-Level Statistics
You can gather segment-level statistics to help you spot performance problems associated
with individual segments. Collecting and viewing segment-level statistics is a good way to
effectively identify hot tables or indexes in an instance.
After viewing wait events and system statistics to identify the performance problem, you can
use segment-level statistics to find specific tables or indexes that are causing the problem.
Consider, for example, that V$SYSTEM_EVENT indicates that buffer busy waits cause a fair
amount of wait time. You can select from V$SEGMENT_STATISTICS the top segments that
cause the buffer busy waits. Then you can focus your effort on eliminating the problem in
those segments.
You can query segment-level statistics through the following dynamic performance views:
ò
V$SEGSTAT_NAME: This view lists the segment statistics being collected and the
properties of each statistic (for instance, if it is a sampled statistic).
ò
V$SEGSTAT: This is a highly efficient, real-time monitoring view that shows the statistic
value, statistic name, and other basic information.
ò
V$SEGMENT_STATISTICS: This is a user-friendly view of statistic values. In addition to all
the columns of V$SEGSTAT, it has information about such things as the segment owner
and table space name. It makes the statistics easy to understand, but it is more costly.
See Also:
Oracle Database Reference for information about dynamic performance views
Chapter 10
Instance Tuning Steps
10-11
Implement and Measure Change
Often at the end of a tuning exercise, it is possible to identify two or three changes that
could potentially alleviate the problem. To identify which change provides the most
benefit, it is recommended that only one change be implemented at a time. The effect
of the change should be measured against the baseline data measurements found in
the problem definition phase.
Typically, most sites with dire performance problems implement several overlapping
changes at once, and thus cannot identify which changes provided any benefit.
Although this is not immediately an issue, this becomes a significant hindrance if
similar problems subsequently appear, because it is not possible to know which of the
changes provided the most benefit and which efforts to prioritize.
If it is not possible to implement changes separately, then try to measure the effects of
dissimilar changes. For example, measure the effect of making an initialization change
to optimize redo generation separately from the effect of creating a new index to
improve the performance of a modified query. It is impossible to measure the benefit of
performing an operating system upgrade if SQL is tuned, the operating system disk
layout is changed, and the initialization parameters are also changed at the same time.
Performance tuning is an iterative process. It is unlikely to find a 'silver bullet' that
solves an instance-wide performance problem. In most cases, excellent performance
requires iteration through the performance tuning phases, because solving one
bottleneck often uncovers another (sometimes worse) problem.
Knowing when to stop tuning is also important. The best measure of performance is
user perception, rather than how close the statistic is to an ideal value.
Interpreting Oracle Database Statistics
Gather statistics that cover the time when the instance had the performance problem.
If you previously captured baseline data for comparison, then you can compare the
current data to the data from the baseline that most represents the problem workload.
When comparing two reports, ensure that the two reports are from times where the
system was running comparable workloads.
Examine Load
Usually, wait events are the first data examined. However, if you have a baseline
report, then check to see if the load has changed. Regardless of whether you have a
baseline, it is useful to see whether the resource usage rates are high.
Load-related statistics to examine include redo size, session logical reads, db block
changes, physical reads, physical read total bytes, physical writes, physical
write total bytes, parse count (total), parse count (hard), and user calls. This
data is queried from V$SYSSTAT. It is best to normalize this data over seconds and over
transactions. It is also useful to examine the total I/O load in MB per second by using
the sum of physical read total bytes and physical write total bytes. The combined value
includes the I/O's used to buffer cache, redo logs, archive logs, by Recovery Manager
(RMAN) backup and recovery and any Oracle Database background process.
Chapter 10
Interpreting Oracle Database Statistics
10-12
In the AWR report, look at the Load Profile section. The data has been normalized over
transactions and over seconds.
Changing Load
The load profile statistics over seconds show the changes in throughput (that is, whether the
instance is performing more work each second). The statistics over transactions identify
changes in the application characteristics by comparing these to the corresponding statistics
from the baseline report.
High Rates of Activity
Examine the statistics normalized over seconds to identify whether the rates of activity are
very high. It is difficult to make blanket recommendations on high values, because the
thresholds are different on each site and are contingent on the application characteristics, the
number and speed of CPUs, the operating system, the I/O system, and the Oracle Database
release.
The following are some generalized examples (acceptable values vary at each site):
ò
A hard parse rate of more than 100 a second indicates that there is a very high amount of
hard parsing on the system. High hard parse rates cause serious performance issues
and must be investigated. Usually, a high hard parse rate is accompanied by latch
contention on the shared pool and library cache latches.
ò
Check whether the sum of the wait times for library cache and shared pool latch events
(latch: library cache, latch: library cache pin, latch: library cache lock and latch: shared
pool) is significant compared to statistic DB time found in V$SYSSTAT. If so, examine the
SQL ordered by Parse Calls section of the AWR report.
ò
A high soft parse rate could be in the rate of 300 a second or more. Unnecessary soft
parses also limit application scalability. Optimally, a SQL statement should be soft parsed
once in each session and executed many times.
Using Wait Event Statistics to Drill Down to Bottlenecks
Whenever an Oracle process wait
